I Blame My Mother for Making Me Reliant
Nice to meet you Sunim. I'm 30 years old.
I feel that my mother is to blame
for me being reliant.
As I blame her, I feel anger
and suffer headaches.
As I'm unhappy, I've been practicing
bowing for repentance.
Should I change my way of thinking
and take full responsibility by
placing blame on myself?
Would it help to think that
I alone am to blame?
Suppose you were kidnapped
by someone.
The kidnapper drugged you
against your own will.
A year passed since then and
you've become a drug addict.
The kidnapper finally released you.
You wouldn't have wanted drugs if they
hadn't first been forced upon you.
But although you've been released,
you now seek drugs yourself.
Treading back on the cause,
where did the issue stem from?
The kidnapper started the issue,
did he not?
Hence you may say it's his problem
and not yours,
although it's your health that is at risk.
He made you do it. Hence
you'd think he should fix the problem.
You are thinking in such way right now.
We investigate causes as a way
to find a solution.
In this case, the cause was clearly
the kidnapper, not yourself.
And yet you are the one
who is addicted to drugs now.
If you impute responsibility to him
to fix your issue,
you'll ultimately ruin yourself.
Regardless of the cause, it is best
for you to resolve your issue.
Hence you should quit taking drugs.
If you are still held captive by force,
then it's different.
But the kidnapper is gone.
Now it's your own problem to solve.
Suppose you've been sexually assaulted
or enslaved.
You were sold into sexual slavery
for three years.
You've been rescued,
yet you're now caught up
in the lifestyle and can't get out.
It is no use blaming the kidnapper
for your misery.
Blaming him does not solve anything
in your life.
Even if the kidnapper is to blame
for initially causing the problem,
it is now your problem to bear and endure.
Buddha once said,
"Although you can't avoid the first arrow,
you can avoid the second one."
You must accept it as your own problem.
Now I often talk about
how influential parents are,
and how parents should
be to their children.
Children misinterpret my words and say,
"Ah, my parents are to blame
for all my faults."
This is not the right approach for the
child to take towards his/her parents.
Let's say you really do
lack sense of independence
due to your parents being overprotective.
Parents should no longer interfere with
the child's life
so that he can stand on his own feet.
But it is most important that
the child makes his own effort to
become independent.
While making effort, blaming parents
does not help.
It only breeds resentment.
There are two consequences to this;
He either resents and disobeys,
or he continues asking for
financial support.
The common case is that
he ends up asking for money.
He starts a business and goes bankrupt.
Then he asks for more money.
Regardless of what parents say,
he'd ignore them and do as he wants
Then he'd repeat the same cycle endlessly.
The parents will suffer from the matter,
the child will also suffer from
having been brought up this way.
Parents should break the cycle
They should consider it do or die
and break it then and there.
Even when the child is facing difficulty,
they should not help
From the child's side, he should cut off
all support from parents
No matter how hard times become,
he shouldn't ask for a helping hand.
He should do whatever
he can to stand on his own feet.
So how should this questioner pray?
"Thank you mother and father."
"Thank you for giving birth to me,
raising me and caring for me."
"I will try my best to repay you
for all you have given me."
He should pray in such way.
Only then can the habit of reliance end.